Finding Aid for Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company records, 1866-1928
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company records
1866-1928
Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company.
85538 Bb.2 2
Records of the Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company of Saginaw, Michigan and Duluth, Minnesota. Correspondence and financial papers concerning company land and lumbering enterprises, and later activities in home building, silo construction, and silage production; records of A.J. Stevens & Co. and McClure-Stevens Land Company of Gladwin, Michigan also business files and diaries of company co-founder, William C. McClure.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11 linear feet
10 microfilms
The record group was the gift of Mrs. Grace S. McClure (donor no. 629 ) and came to the library in 1954.
The record group is open to research.
William C. McClure was born in Ohio in 1842. In 1865, following service in the Civil War, McClure worked for the Mitchell & Rowland Lumber Company of Toledo as a book-keeper. In 1867, he moved to Michigan becoming the company's general agent. In 1869, he began working for the John McGraw & Co. of Bay City. In 1879, in association with Jethro Mitchell of Cincinnati and John A. Hamilton of Toledo, and under the company name of Hamilton, McClure & Co., the three men purchased the mill of W.R. Burt & Co., one of the principal sawmills on the Saginaw River. With Hamilton's death in 1886, the business was reorganized under the name of Mitchell & McClure. About this time, as their lumber tracts in Michigan began to diminish, the firm began purchasing and grouping together large tracts of pine lands near Duluth, Minnesota. The company began construction of a mill here and worked to develop eastern, as well as mid-western markets for their lumber products.
The record group is divided into the following series: Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company; William C. McClure materials; Other Business Enterprises; and Financial records. In addition to the records of the company, the record group includes documentation of other enterprises, such as home building and silo construction and silage production. There are also some records of the A.J. Stevens Land Company of Gladwin, Michigan. The William C. McClure series is important for the run of personal diaries maintained by McClure in the period of 1872-1903.
Subjects:
Business records.; Construction industry.; Crime.; Gladwin (Mich.)--Businesses.; Land use--Michigan.; Logging--Michigan.; Lumbering--Michigan.; Minnesota.; Saginaw (Mich.)--Businesses.; Silos.; Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company.
Contributors:
A.J. Stevens & Co.; McClure, William C., 1842-1904.; McClure-Stevens Land Company.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.
- Mitchell and McClure Lumber Company
  - Business Papers
    (includes deeds, work reports, contracts, patents, tax statements, and related materials)
    - Undated (Box 1)
      (folder 1-1)
    - 1886-1889 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-2)
    - 1890 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-3)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-4)
    - 1895 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-5)
    - 1896 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-6)
    - 1897 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-7)
    - 1898 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-8)
    - 1899-1900 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-9)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-10; 1-11)
    - 1903 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-12)
    - 1904 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-13)
    - 1905 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-14)
    - 1906 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-15)
    - 1907 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-16)
    - 1908 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-17)
    - 1909 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-18; 1-19)
    - 1910 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-20)
    - 1911 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-21)
    - 1912 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-22)
    - 1913 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-23)
    - 1914 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-24)
    - 1915-1925, 1928 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-25)
  - Correspondence (chronological)
    - 1871-1880, undated (Box 2)
      (folder 2-1)
    - 1881-1883 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-2)
    - 1884 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-3)
    - 1885-1890 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-4)
    - 1891-1894 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-5)
    - Regarding Pinkerton Agency investigation of land claims in Minnesota, 1895-1896 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-6)
    - 1895-1897 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-7)
    - 1898-1899 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-8)
    - 1900-1901 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-9)
    - 1902 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-10)
    - 1903 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-11)
    - 1904-1905 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-12)
    - 1906 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-13)
    - With Homer Guerry, Washington, D.C. attorney, 1916-1918; 6 folders (Box 2)
      (folder 2-14---2-19)
    - 1907-1909 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-20)
    - With the Chapman Lumber Co., San Francisco, Calif., 1910-1917 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-21)
    - 1910-1911 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-22)
    - 1912 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-23)
    - 1913 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-24)
    - 1914 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-25)
    - 1915-1917 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-26)
    - 1918-1919 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-27)
    - 1920-1927 (Box 2)
      (folder 2-28)
  - Correspondence (chronological/alphabetical)
    - A-Z, 1895-1902; 10 folders (Box 3)
    - A-L, 1903; 27 folders (Box 3)
    - M-Z, 1903; 19 folders (Box 4)
    - A-Hi, 1904-1905; 13 folders (Box 4)
    - Ho-Z, 1904-1905; 19 folders (Box 5)
    - A-C and M-R (lacking other letters), 1906-1909; 16 folders (Box 5)
    - A-H, 1906-1923; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - I-Z, 1906-1923; 14 folders (Box 6)
  - Letterpress books
    - 1880-1890 (Box 8)
    - 1893-1902 (Box 8)
    - 1896-1897 (Box 8)
    - 1897-1901 (Box 9)
    - 1901-1902 (Box 9)
    - 1902-1920 (Box 9)
    - 1903 (Box 9)
    - 1904 (Box 9)
    - 1904-1907 (Box 9)
    - 1905-1909 (Box 10)
    - 1907-1913 (Box 10)
    - 1913-1920 (Box 10)
  - W.S. Conklin (General. Manager, Saginaw office) correspondence
    - 1903, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - 1904, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - 1905, 3 folders (Box 6)
    - A-Z, 1903-1906; 11 folders (Box 6)
    - A-L, 1906-1907; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - C-Z, 1906-1907; 8 folders (Box 7)
    - A-Z, 1908; 7 folders (Box 7)
    - A-Z, 1909; 8 folders (Box 7)
    - A-Z, 1910; 7 folders (Box 7)
    - A-Z, 1911-1912; 9 folders (Box 7)
- William C. McClure
  - Estate
    - Estate trial balance, 1920-1921 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-26)
    - Estate trial balance, 1922-1923 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-27)
    - Estate trial balance, 1924-1928 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-28)
    - Correspondence A-Z, 1913-1925; 9 folders (Box 8)
  - Diaries
    - 1872 (Box 8)
    - 1873 (Box 8)
    - 1876 (Box 8)
    - 1877-1878 (Box 8)
    - 1880-1881 (Box 8)
    - 1881-1882 (Box 8)
    - 1883 (Box 8)
    - 1884 (Box 8)
    - 1886 (Box 8)
    - 1888 (Box 8)
    - 1889 (Box 8)
    - 1893-1894 (Box 8)
    - 1895 (Box 8)
    - 1900-1901 (Box 8)
    - 1902-February 1903 (Box 8)
- Other Business Enterprises
  - Time Book, October 1890-February 1892 (Box 8)
  - McClure Land Company Minute Book, 1908-1914 (Box 8)
  - McClure Land Company Journal, 1908-1914 (Box 10)
  - McClure Land Company and Estate of William C. McClure, Letter Book, 1903-1927 (Box 10)
  - McClure Company Sales Manual (home construction) (Box 11)
  - McClure Company Sales Manual (silo construction) (Box 11)
  - McClure Company and National Farm Feed Company Files (Box 11)
    (contains general correspondence and files of agents in the "Sugar Jack" promotion of National Farm Feed Company)
  - A.J. Stevens Co. (owner of Mitchell & McClure lands)
    - Trial Balances, 1902 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-29)
    - Trial Balances, 1903 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-30)
    - Trial Balances, 1904-1905 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-31)
    - Trial Balances, 1906 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-32)
    - Trial Balances, 1907 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-33)
    - Trial Balances, 1908 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-34)
    - Trial Balances, 1909 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-35)
    - Financial papers, 1910-1912 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-36)
  - McClure-Stevens Land Co.
    - Trial Balances, 1912-1913 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-37)
    - Trial Balances, 1914-1915 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-38)
    - Trial Balances, 1916-1917 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-39)
    - Trial Balances, 1918-1924 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-40)
  - Spring River (Missouri) Mining Co. (Pres., William McClure)
    - Papers, 1897-1902 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-41)
    - Financial Statements, 1897-1898 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-42)
    - Financial Statements, 1899 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-43)
    - Financial Statements, 1900-1901 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-44)
  - Island Club (summer resort) East Saginaw, Michigan
    - 1885-1891 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-45)
  - Saginaw Construction Company
    - Trial Balances, 1888 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-46)
  - Vermillion Lumber Co.
    - Trial Balances, 1893-1895 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-47)
  - Farmers Handy Wagon (Box 1)
    (folder 1-48)
  - Mitchell-Dorr Realty Co.
    - Balance Sheets, 1925; 1927; 1928 (Box 1)
      (folder 1-49)
- Financial records (microfilm), positive microfilm
  - Ledger, 1866-1867 (Box 12, Reel 1)
  - Ledger, 1868-1874 (Box 12, Reel 1)
  - Ledger, 1885-1891 (Box 12, Reel 2)
  - Ledger, 1891-1895 (Box 12, Reel 2)
  - Ledger, 1896-1900 (Box 12, Reel 2)
  - Ledger, 1890-1894 (Box 12, Reel 3)
  - Ledger, 1891-1894 (Box 12, Reel 3)
  - Ledger, 1901-1920 (Box 12, Reel 3)
  - Ledger, 1903-1928 (Box 12, Reel 4)
  - Journal-Saginaw, 1885-1890 (Box 12, Reel 4)
  - Journal-Saginaw, 1890-1892 (Box 12, Reel 4)
  - Journal-Saginaw, 1903-1928 (Box 12, Reel 4)
  - Journal-Duluth, 1891-1893 (Box 12, Reel 5)
  - Journal-Duluth, 1893-1895 (Box 12, Reel 5)
  - Journal-Duluth, 1896-1898 (Box 12, Reel 6)
  - Journal-Duluth, 1898-1900 (Box 12, Reel 6)
  - Journal-Duluth, 1901-1904 (Box 12, Reel 7)
  - Journal-Saginaw, 1904-1920 (Box 12, Reel 7)
  - Journal-Saginaw (East Side), 1890-1894 (Box 12, Reel 7)
  - Journal-Saginaw (East Side), 1891-1894 (Box 12, Reel 7)
  - Cash Book-Duluth, February 1891-April 1894 (Box 12, Reel 8)
  - Cash Book-Duluth, May 1894-December 1895 (Box 12, Reel 8)
  - Cash Book-Duluth, January 1895-October 1898 (Box 12, Reel 9)
  - Cash Book-Duluth, October 1898-December 1900 (Box 12, Reel 9)
  - Cash Book-Duluth-Saginaw, January 1901-December 1908 (Box 12, Reel 10)
  - Cash Book-Saginaw, January 1890-December 1894 (Box 12, Reel 10)
  - Cash Book-Saginaw, December 1902-March 1904 (Box 12, Reel 10)
  - Cash Book-Saginaw, January 1909-July 1920 (Box 12, Reel 10)
  - Trial Balance Book, 1891-1894; 1900-1920 (Box 12, Reel 10)
  - Production and Shipments, 1891-1898 (Box 12, Reel 10)